<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sharegrowblog</title>
    <description>for inspiration, tips and true stories about job hunting
</description>
    <link>http://www.sharegrow.eu/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.sharegrow.eu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 17:56:31 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 17:56:31 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>A career in medical research</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;could-you-tell-us-something-about-your-current-work&quot;&gt;Could you tell us something about your current work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently working as a Clinical Research Associate at King’s College London (university). This means that I am in a full time position; where I work part time as a MPhil researcher on a PhD and part time as a medical doctor (M.D.) in the hospital. In my case this is research on autism at the Forensic and Neurodevelopmental Science department, and as a consultant doctor at the policlinics Autism and ADHD at the Maudsley hospital (part of King’s College Hospitals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am very happy with the versatility of this job and the possibilities to develop myself, my talents, my interests and it has plenty of opportunities to go into (and choose from where you want to get in to).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;did-you-follow-official-education-for-this-job-or-did-they-hire-you-because-they-had-faith-in-your-qualities&quot;&gt;Did you follow official education for this job or did they hire you because they had faith in your qualities?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did follow education both for clinical work and for research; medical degree/masters and research masters in life sciences. As this is not an extraordinary combination of studies, I believe I have been hired in this particular job and institute for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the extra addition to science from being a medical doctor. For many research projects in psychiatry, tissue samples like blood samples must be taken, health checks are necessary, and drugs are administered. Therefore it is an advantage for the team to have medical doctors walking around and working at the same department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being enthusiast about both psychiatry and science, which is visible in my CV. This may have given my current employer the idea that I was reliable when it comes to sticking to this job for over 5 years. It is an investment for the employer to have me (e.g. I did not work before with neuroimaging and they have to spent a lot of time and money in me to train me) but they expect me to deliver good and long-term work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Last but not least, I believe (especially now after I have started working here) that it is very important for an employer that your personality fits the team. A team needs to consist of different personality types, not everyone can be a leader, but not everyone may be as perfectionist, or creative. I think I very well fit in the team, I add something (medical perspective and experience) and my colleagues help me where my weaknesses lie (e.g. programming, statistics, science of neuroimaging).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;could-you-tell-us-something-about-how-you-have-found-this-job&quot;&gt;Could you tell us something about how you have found this job?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first wrote down what exactly what I wanted to learn and what goals to reach within my career. Then I looked around what ways there are to get there (for me becoming a psychiatrist is the main goal, PhD or no PhD is a decision I had to make). And then decided in what countries/cities I wanted to work depending on where the schools are really good or the research is focused on something of my interest. This already narrowed down the options. I weekly or bi-weekly searched for vacancies for all these options/universities of my choice. As well as applying for jobs, I also started asking around if anyone in my circles may have contacts with people already working in these universities so that I could talk with someone in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly for the job I have now, an old student-colleague of mine from Amsterdam was working now in a position which was exactly what I wanted already in a University of my choice. So I approached him and we talked things over, so I had an idea of what my chances where getting a job there. I started attending lectures of professors at that university so I could at least show my face. And I ended up emailing the director of a team I was interested in working with. This was a great entry, because they now knew about me, my CV, and my wish to work with them. And then I have been kept updated by the team directly about what position where coming up and they proposed me to apply. So I applied for the positions they told may suit me and not long after I did get invited for an interview for one of the applications I did and I finally got the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-have-also-worked-in-fashion-can-you-tell-us-about-your-choice-to-rather-opt-for-psychiatryresearch&quot;&gt;You have also worked in fashion, can you tell us about your choice to rather opt for psychiatry/research?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work in fashion as a seamstress and/or designer can go two ways: either you can work at a company and the whole day just design or just sew, or you can start your own business and design/sew one month per year but then you will have to be looking for funds, providing press, liaising with shops or set up pop-up sales by yourself for the rest of the year. I realized that both of these options were not my dream and have chosen not to work full-time in fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-did-you-have-your-largest-dip-during-your-searching-process&quot;&gt;When did you have your largest dip during your searching process?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably when I finally got into knowing what I wanted and what locations I wanted to focus on. I then found quite a lot of vacancies to where applicable to my skills and needs, but many of those jobs were not exactly what I wanted. Nevertheless I needed a job so I applied for all the jobs that seemed ok. I then ended up doing quite a lot of interviews and had to let interviews down because both would be at the same date, and it was bit depressing because I wanted a job but at the same time did not find ‘exactly’ what I wanted and couldn’t choose really between two or more equally bad propositions. I ended up taking a job which was very nice but not exactly my dream job, and I have been doing for just a short amount of time until I was certain I would get this position in London. So I just continued applying for the ‘amazing’ jobs. (not amazing for my last employer, but better for me of course!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-according-to-you-does-not-work-at-all-when-you-want-to-find-a-position-abroad-or-in-general&quot;&gt;What, according to you, does not work at all when you want to find a position (abroad or in general)?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does not work at all I think is: applying for jobs you don’t really want, or don’t really have the skills for just because you want a job. Also, when you are very vague about your motivations (of why you want that job and what you want to lear there, what you want to do after, what you can add to the team), because an employer want to make sure you have defined goals in you life that the position he/she offers can help you with reaching these goals and so you have specific/defined things you will be working on and serving as a guideline to see if you are developing yourself enough in that position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-wisdom-have-you-gathered-and-which-tip-would-you-like-to-share-with-others&quot;&gt;What wisdom have you gathered and which tip would you like to share with others?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My suggestion is: be clear, and be specific of your needs, skills and weaknesses. And directly link those things with hypothetical experiences that you will have in that future job that will make you work on these weaknesses, improve yourself and reach your goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I realise that in the UK and in France employers are continuously looking for new talent already before a new job position has been created. Therefore they often end up already having people in line that they would like to take into the company once (the money for) a position has came up. It is best to try and get in contact directly with someone of that company, have your name dropped, and (if possible) show your face so you will be remembered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-said-that-its-smart-to-beforehand-anticipate-on-qualities-that-you-feel-need-to-be-developed-how-did-you-work-on-your-weaknesses-before-you-were-confronted-with-a-jobinterview&quot;&gt;You said that it’s smart to beforehand anticipate on qualities that you feel need to be developed. How did you work on your weaknesses before you were confronted with a job/interview?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have chosen to prepare for a job in a Neuroimaging Science course in programming through Coursera. When they asked me whether I was able to program I could indicate that I (still) had no experience with neuroimaging studies, but I am motivated to learn and that I even started following a course in statistical analysis of neuroimaging data. You can then show that you realize you lack knowledge, but that you are motivated to learn at your job.
Another example might be that I had never really written a full scientific article. I did write many other things, but all in a different context. In this case I said that I liked writing as an “activity”, which is also clearly visible in my CV , as I did many other writing activities and therefore am interested in writing, but for a different target group and from another topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-the-last-question-you-often-just-seems-to-attract-the-plunge-and-space-for-yourself-to-demand-you-can-respond-to-the-following-statement-fortune-favors-the-bold&quot;&gt;And the last question, you often just seems to attract the plunge and space for yourself to demand, you can respond to the following statement? &lt;em&gt;Fortune favors the bold.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haha, a nice statement, I have to think about that. Perhaps this is an answer: I will never forget that my grandmother told me when I was 10 years old and very shy; “Hester if you remain so shy, you’ll never get anywhere.” It has impressed me so much, I believe even had to cry later because I realized how much my grandmother was right. And of course I wanted to get somewhere, because I wanted that my grandmother and my family would be proud of me. It is true that I was shy. So much that I dared to give almost no response even in the classroom when the teacher would ask me something, let alone that I would speak up to someone else myself. I was the typical example of the person standing at the checkout waiting and never get her turn because every once again for someone else jumped the cue again. With great difficulty I have tried to change this and I have become increasingly assertive.
The word “bold” might sound negative, but in the core of the saying, I must admit, is a lot of truth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sharegrow.eu/2016/12/25/Hester.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sharegrow.eu/2016/12/25/Hester.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jobs in her field are extremely scarce</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;could-you-tell-us-something-about-your-current-work&quot;&gt;Could you tell us something about your current work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently working as Head of Development for an independent film production company in East London. We make low-budget films and my job is to help pick the projects (screenplays) we want to film and to work together with the writers to improve their scripts and get them ready for production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-are-you-happy-with-this-job&quot;&gt;Why are you happy with this job?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t be happier with my job. It’s a small company so I get to work across a lot of different tasks which keeps my job interesting and diverse. I also love working with scripts and story. It’s fun to assess the potential of a script when it first comes in and then to see how a story can be improved. The difference a strong script can make to a film is huge and I’m a big advocate for not filming before the script is ready!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;did-you-follow-official-education-for-this-job-or-did-they-hire-you-because-they-had-faith-in-your-qualities&quot;&gt;Did you follow official education for this job or did they hire you because they had faith in your qualities?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes and no. I did a BA in Liberal Arts followed by an MA in English literature neither of which were super relevant to my job. But then I also did a diploma in practical filmmaking which is definitely relevant. I was originally hired as an office/production assistant and was lucky enough to find a niche within the company. Script reading was one of my stronger skills and interests and as no one had really taken on that script development role within the company so there was an opportunity for me to step in. With the support of my company I enrolled into a part-time diploma course in Script Development at the NFTS (which is one of the best film schools in England) and that set me up for my current position as Head of Development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;could-you-tell-us-something-about-how-you-have-found-this-job&quot;&gt;Could you tell us something about how you have found this job?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I completed my practical filmmaking diploma course I managed to get a few commissions as a writer and I was doing (unpaid) internships at the same time with different film production companies in London. I was lucky enough to have parents who could support me during this time but I have noticed that unpaid internships seem to be part and parcel of trying to find a job in a highly-competitive creative industry which is obviously not a fair situation. But the companies I worked at were generally quite small and offered genuine learning opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These internships rarely turn into jobs and usually companies will have a constant rotation of interns. The ones I did  were really helpful in terms of gaining more experience, names to put on my CV, and in terms of making new industry connections. I found it important that I learned something from the internship so it wasn’t just me genuinely working for free. I turned down one internship with a big production company because the internship amounted to doing actual skilled work for free and I just couldn’t see the benefit of that even if the name would look good on my CV. I thought that was pretty exploitative as they had produced 7 HUGE blockbusters and were only paying their interns £40 a week just to read novels for them… (Reading novels for production companies is a skill because you are asked to read and assess the potential of the work for film adaptation - other companies were paying me for this skill so to have a constant supply of interns doing this for free when a company is worth billions is just infuriating to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I also did some freelance work as a film producer and of course I was working nearly fulltime at a pub to get by which was great because the hours were flexible and it wasn’t intellectually demanding which allowed me to stay mentally focused on my job search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s tricky to get your foot in the door because there is so much competition. I applied for loads of jobs, met a lot of people, and eventually I was lucky enough to get hired in an entry-level role. At the time I didn’t think I would still be with this company now but I was even more lucky because I ended up in a team that valued my contributions and gave me room to grow within my role. I think a lot of companies, especially in the film industry, can be a bit hierarchical whereas my boss was always very focused on making sure everyone felt valued and included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-did-you-have-your-largest-dip-during-your-searching-process&quot;&gt;When did you have your largest dip during your searching process?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I’d spent about a year working at the pub I did loose morale a little bit. The pub was getting tedious and I was starting to reach a point where I needed to consider the possibility that maybe I wouldn’t manage to get my foot in the door and that I needed to become self-sufficient (which I wasn’t yet at the time as the pub was paying way less than London living wage..) What helped for me was that there really wasn’t any other option. If you want to work in film then that’s just what you’re going to do and you’ll keep trying until happens because you don’t really see your life going any other way. Or at least that was my experience. I was raised to be very ambitious and career-oriented so that might have also had something to do with but I was definitely not going to give up on the film dream. (And of course I was privileged enough to have parents who were able and willing to support me in this pursuit - otherwise it would have been a lot more difficult).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-according-to-you-does-not-work-at-all-when-you-want-to-find-a-position-abroad-or-in-general&quot;&gt;What, according to you, does not work at all when you want to find a position (abroad or in general)?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I’m sceptical of is online job applications. In general I think you need to have a way in that is a bit more personal than a general application. We get tons of general enquiries and unfortunately they all end up being deleted. I think if you apply online your CV is one of 100s and that makes it so hard to stand out. Whereas if you have an in somehow, through someone you know who knows someone at the company or something like that, that gives you a big advantage. Even with the part time jobs I did (waitress, sales associate, barmaid), I ALWAYS got those jobs after going into the business in person and dropping off my CV to the manager (not some random person) and usually following up with a second in-person visit if I didn’t hear anything for some time. People like to see the face behind the CV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-wisdom-have-you-gathered-and-which-tip-would-you-like-to-share-with-others&quot;&gt;What wisdom have you gathered and which tip would you like to share with others?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think the most important thing is creating opportunities for yourself because you will get so many No’s before you get a Yes. Seek out people who are already doing the job you would like to have and see if they’ll give you 20 minutes of their time for a coffee and some advice and maybe they can put you on to someone else to speak to and by the end of it you’ll have made a whole bunch of new contacts within your desired industry. Also, apply to things online but don’t put all your eggs in that basket. Sign up to your school’s alumni schemes, speak to your former teachers, your parents’ friends, anyone who might know someone who could help you make a start. Put out calls on facebook and join industry facebook groups (I’m a member of several groups on Facebook dedicated to people working in film that constantly put up job opportunities). And of course try to think of different paths that might lead to your destination. There are many different ways to get started in film for example so be open to trying different strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And be patient. In my experience our generation is finding it very difficult to get their first job. My boyfriend recently graduated from his BA and is also going through unpaid internships now while working at the pub. Hopefully he’ll be getting a more steady income but I imagine it will take at least a year for him to find his feet. There’s that annoying Catch 22 where companies want you to already have experience before you can get a job that would allow you to gain experience. It sucks. But I think that with tenacity and patience and a willingness to do a job you may be overqualified for while living in a crappy house share with several people to save on rent you should be fine! (at least in London)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sharegrow.eu/2016/12/21/Jolien.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sharegrow.eu/2016/12/21/Jolien.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stretching her possibilities in Paris</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I got the chance to interview Denise who moved from the Netherlands to Paris a couple of years ago. We talked about the challenges of job-hunting in the city of lights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;could-you-tell-us-something-about-your-current-position&quot;&gt;Could you tell us something about your current position?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently I’m working as an assistant for an American fitness company. They provide personal training, nutrition programs and arrange other requested services for high end clients. I’m happy with this job, because it’s in my area of expertise, which was difficult to find because I don’t speak French. This way, I progress in my work field. Also, it’s just a few hours a week, which is also very welcome after my previous, demanding job in a restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;did-you-follow-official-education-for-this-job-or-did-they-hire-you-because-they-had-faith-in-your-qualities&quot;&gt;Did you follow official education for this job or did they hire you because they had faith in your qualities?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that I successfully completed a 4 year education in sports, fitness and well-being was definitely a contributing factor in me getting this job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;could-you-tell-us-something-about-how-you-have-found-this-job&quot;&gt;Could you tell us something about how you have found this job?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, this job fell right into my lap. I had resigned from working in at my previous job as a server in an American diner. I left on very good terms; my boss was sad to see me go. One day he called me to ask if I was interested in a job, because he knew someone who was looking to hire. He introduced us to each other, leading to employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-did-you-have-your-largest-dip-during-your-searching-process&quot;&gt;When did you have your largest dip during your searching process?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest dip when I first started to look for a job, almost 3 years ago, even before working in the restaurant, was discovering the importance of language and employment. I had underestimated this. Since I work in the fitness industry, I assumed that this was an industry dominated by the English language which I master sufficiently. But, in France, you need to be able to speak French. At one point, it became clear to me, that it was not going to happen, with the level of French I had. I needed almost a week to deal with the disappointment, before redirecting my job search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-according-to-you-does-not-work-at-all-when-you-want-to-find-a-position-abroad-or-in-general&quot;&gt;What, according to you, does not work at all when you want to find a position (abroad or in general)?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that when you are looking for work, in a foreign country, you have to be willing to be creative and open your search spectrum, especially when you have a beginners level of the language. It might very well be possible that whatever job you have in mind, is not going to be possible for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the same time, you can take this as a challenge to work somewhere you would have never expected to work. I see this as a challenge and an upside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-wisdom-have-you-gathered-and-which-tip-would-you-like-to-share-with-others&quot;&gt;What wisdom have you gathered and which tip would you like to share with others?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What helped me is being able to allow myself time to find a job. Most people want that as quick as possible, I did too, but I had to accept that it was going to take longer. For me, it wasn’t an option to job hunt for 40 hours a week. So I spent a certain amount of time on the job hunt, and the rest with discovering the city, joining online groups of people in the same position and practicing my hobbies. That is what I needed, and I advise you to listen to yourself and your needs too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sharegrow.eu/2016/11/01/Denise.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sharegrow.eu/2016/11/01/Denise.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
